{"posts":[null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,{"tags":[{"name":"Forums"},{"name":"Assignments"},{"name":"Assignment 1"},{"name":"Assignment 1 Specification"}],"question":" \"Bad address in data/stack read\" error. Anyone have an idea of what the problem could be? Spent nearly a whole day trying to figure out what the issue is :'( It's printing a bunch of errors: According to qtspim, it's failing on the line I've highlighted in the code. I've done some testing and for some reason if I try to print the byte at display[row][out_col] 's address, it's fine, but it screws up if i try to print the byte at bigString[row][in_col] 's address... Any ideas appreciated!! ","answers":[" Why are you trying to print the bigString byte? bigString is only for inout. In any case, the output you've sent is giving plenty of clues. It's telling you which instruction. It's telling you the address being used. You know that this instruction is using the address contained in $t4 . Now find out which instruction set the value of $t4 incorrectly. Then work out why. (A loop that hasn't terminated? An invalid offset calculation?) ",[" I'm trying to print out bigString to see what characters are being stored there. Anyhow, thank you for the advice! I'll test them out and see if I can pinpoint where the issue lies. "]]},{"tags":[{"name":"Forums"},{"name":"Assignments"},{"name":"Assignment 1"},{"name":"Assignment 1 Specification"}],"question":" And \"exception occurred at PC=0x004003f0\" I am getting these errors when attempting to run the code, i was just wondering if it is a problem with a loop or with wrong calculation of address, and so how do i tell if address is out of bounds? Thank you ","answers":[" The \"bad address\"es it's complaining about are all roughly in the data region (how do you know this?) If it's complaining about \"out of bounds\", then maybe you've gone beyond the end of your defined data structures. If you want to find where the bounds are, look at the \"Data\" tab in QtSpim. QtSpim tells you the value of all registers. If you're using some register as an offset/index, then check that its value hasn't gotten \"too large\" "]},null,null,null,{"tags":[{"name":"Forums"},{"name":"Assignments"},{"name":"Assignment 1"},{"name":"Assignment 1 Specification"}],"question":" I was wondering if my style is good or not (this is just some random code I made up). https://pastebin.com/CKRWnhEr 1. When I comment something, what do I comment? The c code part or what the actual mips code is doing? 2. For example bge is the equivalent of i &lt; j. So do I comment i &lt; j or i &gt;= j 3. Also is there any autotests for this assignment? ","answers":[" Comments that just restate what the instruction is doing are not helpful. You're better to put a single line of C code as a comment over the few MIPS instructions that implement that C code. If you want to put (i &lt; j) somewhere, put it in a block comment before the loop. If you want to put (i &gt;= j), then put a comment like: if (i &gt;= j) break; There are few distinct cases that we can test, so you don't really need auto-tests. As long as it works with one word (e.g. \"hello\") and works for mixed case strings (e.g. \"Hello\") and two words (e.g. \"Hello world\"), and three words (e.g. \"Hello there John\") then it'll work for all of our tests. ",[" Thanks for the reply. Just 2 follow up questions. 1. What is a comment block? (a multiple line description)? 2. I have concerns about how I do the spacing for instructions sets which are 2, 3 and 4 character instruction sets. https://pastebin.com/CKRWnhEr In the above link, the instruction li and add have the registers line up nicely. However in the instruction move ,the registers are not lined up. What would I do? ",[" What is a comment block? (a multiple line description)? A bunch of comments, not appended to instructions, and occurring just before the sequence of MIPS instructions that they're describing. spacing for instructions sets which are 2, 3 and 4 character instruction sets. I think you mean register rather than character ... But, to be consistent with the supplied code, each instruction should be formatted like &lt;TAB&gt;OpCode&lt;TAB&gt;Args where the Args are separated from each other by a comma and a space. ",[" If I follow the same format supplied in the initial code, I will be fine (not lose any marks for style)? "]]]]},null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,{"tags":[{"name":"Forums"},{"name":"Assignments"},{"name":"Assignment 1"},{"name":"Assignment 1 Specification"}],"question":" Hi, I was just wondering how you would found the offset for the 3D array all_chars? ","answers":[" Well the offset for 2D arrays are: ( (row_Index * col_Size) + col_Index) * sizeof(data_type) + base_address. I think if you kind of substitute the 3rd dimension, you'll find it. And it's pretty close to the above formula. "," Think about it like this. The which array has a character for each index. Going into that index you access the matrix representation of that character. So then how might you access 'a' or 'b'. "]},null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,{"tags":[{"name":"Forums"},{"name":"Assignments"},{"name":"Assignment 1"},{"name":"Assignment 1 Specification"}],"question":" Do we need to follow the format of the given code in order to get the styling mark? For example, for our loops, do we need to set labels for init,cond, step as in the main_PTRs_init, main_PTRs_cond main_PTRs_step ? Or is it fine to leave it like this? init_loop_ i： (if...then j to endi) init_loop_ j: (if.... j to end j) j++ j init_loop_ j endj: i++.. j init_loop_i endi: Thank you. ","answers":[" Pick a style and be consistent. So long as that style is not totally illegible, you're pretty likely to get the style mark. The style I've used is intended to make it easy to see C's control flow points in your assembly program. Many of those labels won't be a branch target, but serve to provide you information. "]},{"tags":[{"name":"Forums"},{"name":"Assignments"},{"name":"Assignment 1"},{"name":"Assignment 1 Specification"}],"question":" Hi. My program has numerous errors that I have no idea as to why they exist. I haven't a clue as to why this occurs. This prevents my program from actually running anything at all. ","answers":[" I'm not sure how to put my actual MIPS file here, for only the 'Course Staff' to see. ",[" I looked at QtSpim and it seems like you're running QtSpim without first loading the exe.s file into QtSpim?? So either do \"1521 qtspim -file exe.s\" or open qtspim then \"Load file\" or \"Reinitialise and Load File\" "]]},null,null,{"tags":[{"name":"Forums"},{"name":"Assignments"},{"name":"Assignment 1"},{"name":"Assignment 1 Specification"}],"question":" Allowed to alter \"delay\" function numbers? I checked the other posts regarding delay and it was not quite clear so I just wanted to verify. Are we allowed to alter the delay function, specifically the $t4 &amp; $t5 values so it prints nicely out on the terminal? Thanks. ","answers":[" The is a post on the front page: \"Tweak the loop bounds in delay until you get decent scrolling speed\". "]},{"tags":[{"name":"Forums"},{"name":"Assignments"},{"name":"Assignment 1"},{"name":"Assignment 1 Specification"}],"question":" Hi there. May I ask can I build a extra function myself (for finding the address of the element of the array). Also I wonder how could I add an argument into Qtspim (like \"Hello there\" ) ","answers":[" Hi there, you are allowed write extra functions :) To add arguments into QtSpim, go to the menu bar, Simulator -&gt; Run Parameters, and you'll be able to enter in your arguments. Word of warning though, you won't be able to test strings that have a space bar - due to the way that QtSpim handles the arguments. ",[" Thank you thanks a lot!! "]]},{"tags":[{"name":"Forums"},{"name":"Assignments"},{"name":"Assignment 1"},{"name":"Assignment 1 Specification"}],"question":" GREEN FLASHES Hi there. When I run my MIPS code, I get flashing green (cursor?) rectangles. You can see an example in the image below. Strangely, this only occurs at certain speeds. At lower speeds, there is no flashing green. I'm not sure if this is a problem with uninitialised array indexes in my code or if my code is ok. I know some others are having the same problem. Would anyone be able to point us in the direction of the bug? Any help would be greatly appreciated. Thanks! ","answers":[" The short answer: we're interested in the characters your code outputs, not how it's painted by a heap of very slow software emulating an even slower terminal. The slightly longer, and less cryptic answer: the approach we're using in painting the marquee to the terminal is extremely naive: for every frame, we clear everything, and then paint everything. In an ideal world, the terminal could work out how to turn this into partial updates of the screen. In practice, what you're seeing is that not happening. The way terminals work hasn't really changed much since 1978, with the introduction of the DEC VT-100 terminal; the terminals we use today, or more accurately, terminal emulators , pretend to be VT-100 relatives of various denominations. These were powered by Intel 8080 processors, running at a blistering two megahertz, and with very nearly no memory, and words like \"optimised display update algorithm\" weren't the domain of hardware. The sequences of characters in the \"clear\" label -- if I recall correctly, something like \\033[H\\033[2J -- is magic to clear all characters on the screen. The terminal emulator meditates upon its idea of what the screen looks like, and updates it, character by character, or sequence by sequence, so each step occurs effectively separately. At low speed, the terminal emulator and the rest of the graphics pipeline can keep up, but at high speed, the terminal has to be painting nearly continuously, which can cause the frame that's pushed into the raster buffer to be incorrect. What you're likely seeing, then, is a weird combination of multiple frames, one fully painted with the cursor placed after the last newline, and one that's being painted, with a cursor being placed before characters are. Exactly what is causing that would be a fun (well, \"fun\") weekend exercise in following data through the baklava-like layers of (thin, flaky, delicious?) abstractions. An interesting challenge (and one not worth marks but worth many, many kudos and/or Mars bars): devise a faster screen painting algorithm for this assignment (or for, say, a visual text editor like Vi or Emacs). There's a few interesting approaches that come to mind ... you may also like a list of all the control sequences you could use to help you out. ",[" Thanks, Jashank! Much appreciated. I will begin research into baklava "]]},{"tags":[{"name":"Forums"},{"name":"Assignments"},{"name":"Assignment 1"},{"name":"Assignment 1 Specification"}],"question":" Hi, I got some questions there. 1.Though we have a .space 81000 there, but the bytes we actually use is 9*10*1000 which is 9000, so just leave other places nothing or a space? 2. for display, at t=0, should we have a column() of the character stored in bigString or should all the column be the column of \" \" Thank you in advance! ","answers":[" Hi, Feng! You questions seem a little bit ambiguous. So for your first question, why are you saying that the actual bytes we use is 9000? Are you saying NSCOLS is at size 9000?But that is not the total bytes we will use, that’s just the number of bytes the bigString colum will use, hence the actual byte bigString uses is multipled by NROWS, and that is the maximum number of bytes it will take. And if you are saying what will happen if the input is shorter than the maximum, then I would recommend you to read through the setUpDisplay function, variable “theLength” is passed to setUpDisply function to tell setUpDisplay to stop setting up as long as it hits the end of your input, so it won’t keep printing until reach the end of the bigString. And for your question 2, are you saying after the first iteration, the program will show the first column of bigString? And yes, it will, since the starting_col is set to NDCOLS-1, and I don’t think we need to make it show nothing in the first iteration, as the assignment specification just asked us to translate the C program, but if you want , u can simply set starting_col to NDCOLS, it will fix the problem . And I also think you have some misunderstandings with respect to bigString and display, because if you want to change the starting column that will show after the first iteration, you should alter the arrary “display” rather than “big String”, as “bigString” constantly stores the “big version” of our input and will not be altered once it is created, and “display” is the actual picture of every frame we see from the command line. ",[" After a communication to her, her first confusion was actually about the calculation of NSCOLS, which is in deed a problem of the code, it was accidentally multiplied by an extra NROWS. Original post: https://webcms3.cse.unsw.edu.au/COMP1521/18s2/forums/2702663 "]]},null,null,null,{"tags":[{"name":"Forums"},{"name":"Assignments"},{"name":"Assignment 1"},{"name":"Assignment 1 Specification"}],"question":" QtSpim issues when used on CSE VLAB machine. In attempts to debug my code, I seemed to have done something to my QtSpim application, as I cannot use it at all. Whenever I attempt to \"Load File\" or \"Reinitalize and load file\" in MIPS, my terminal outputs \"setNativeLocks failed: Resource temporarily unavailable\". Then when I attempt to run or step through my program using QtSpim i get the error \"Exception occurred at PC=0x00040000\" followed by \"Bad address in text read: 0x00040000\" which then continues to output the same error message with the hexidecimal value just incrementing by 4 (\"Exception occurred at PC=0x00040004\"). In the QtSpim window, it always seems to run starting from line [80000180] or the first line in the \"Kernel Text Segment\" and never reaches the \"User Text Segment\" I did attempt logging off and on again, disconnecting and reconnecting to the VPN and loading other assembly files although nothing seemed to work. Hence irrespective of if the assembly code was incorrect, QtSpim did not work. Any help would be greatly appreciated as it makes using QtSpim in VLab impossible. ","answers":[" I'm not sure what the lock problem is. Maybe there are too many people trying to run QtSpim on the VLAB servers. Is it still happening? ",[" It appears everywhere on CSE... I suspect a bug in QtSpim. ",[" I don't ... but why not tell them about xspim? "]]," PC=0x00040000 is where it normally starts running. If there's not a valid instruction at that location, then you would definitely observe the behaviour you describe where it jumps off to the kernel to \"handle\" the error. What appears in the code window before you step through the program? ",[" I tried again just now, it seems I still am having the same issues. I've added screenshots of the issues I detailed above. But basically I open QtSpim, load a file, then press single step and it starts at \"PC=0x80000180\"/the line I display above every time. I have tried using previous exercises which I know work fine, although they did not work, and this program (\"exe.s\" or in this case \"exe_final.s\") works fine on home computer's QtSpim. Although I seem to be unable to use \"run parameters\" on my mac since it crashes hence I tried to use QtSpim on the VLAB to no avail. ",[" Have a careful look at your text segment addresses. The address 0x00040000 is incorrect; it should be 0x00400000. ",[" Thanks Jas and Jashank for the help. It is working now. It seems the \"run parameters\" had the address stuck at 0x00400000. "]]]]},{"tags":[{"name":"Forums"},{"name":"Assignments"},{"name":"Assignment 1"},{"name":"Assignment 1 Specification"}],"question":" Hi, what is the best way to debug my program printing out a chunk of space and no characters? I can't step through in mips because there's so many loops that I'll never reach the end, so are there any common reasons for this happening that I can look into? Thanks. ","answers":[" Qtspim has breakpoints that can be set by right clicking and has a list of each register. ",[" I'm not sure how to figure out using breakpoints whether certain arrays have been filled with a blank rather than a character, how would I go about it? Thanks. ",[" set a break point before you set your display array to stop executing at the trouble spot. Then step through from there to see what value you are saving into the array to make sure its correct. "]]]},null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,null,{"tags":[{"name":"Forums"},{"name":"Assignments"},{"name":"Assignment 1"},{"name":"Assignment 1 Specification"}],"question":" What is the final values of the delay numbers for the scroll.s file when submitting? ","answers":[" anything you want that produces a nice looking output, as long as it is still relatively fast, so it doesn't time out. "]},{"tags":[{"name":"Forums"},{"name":"Assignments"},{"name":"Assignment 1"},{"name":"Assignment 1 Specification"}],"question":" Will only the latest submission be marked ","answers":[" Yes. You can use give as many times as you want before the due date, and only the most recent will be marked. "]},null,null,null,null,null,null,{"tags":[{"name":"Forums"},{"name":"Assignments"},{"name":"Assignment 1"},{"name":"Assignment 1 Specification"}],"question":" Just wondering what the purpose of completing isUpper when it is just the opposite of isLower? Could we leave it out? ","answers":[" It's not \"the opposite\". The two functions are measuring different things. Maybe *in this context* it's not needed, but it would definitely be useful, and distinct from isLower in other contexts. But it was mainly there to be an easy mark tog et started ... because it is so similar to isLower. ",[" Thanks! "]]},{"tags":[{"name":"Forums"},{"name":"Assignments"},{"name":"Assignment 1"},{"name":"Assignment 1 Specification"}],"question":" I know how to implement something like display[i][j] = ' '; in MIPS, after watching this week's lab video ( https://www.soln.io/s/Hk1b3YUUQ?series_id=rJ-ufzvU... ), but I am not sure how to implement bigString[row][col + i * (CHRSIZE+1)] = ' '. Can someone explain how to do this ","answers":[" Jashank did a nice explanation of this (he was getting a value, rather than setting a value, but there's only on line different) in Tuesday's lecture towards the of the first hour. The videos are on echo360 now, and will be on YouTube later today (hopefully ",[" ok ... Jashank's explanation wasn't quite the same ... but principle of computing an offset by arithmetic on indices is the same "]]},null,null,null,null,null,{"tags":[{"name":"Forums"},{"name":"Assignments"},{"name":"Assignment 1"},{"name":"Assignment 1 Specification"}],"question":" scroll speed too slow? ","answers":[" I just posted a Notice on this. The solution is to tweak the loop bounds in the delay function until you get acceptable scrolling speed. "," Do you know how to run the program with a command line argument? I could only manually change a0 and a1 ",[" make 1521 spim -file exe.s String isnt it this? ",[" Thanks, I think by changing the value of the delay number could help "]]]},{"tags":[{"name":"Forums"},{"name":"Assignments"},{"name":"Assignment 1"},{"name":"Assignment 1 Specification"}],"question":" typo in scroll.s &gt; \"String mush be &lt; \" instead of &gt; \"String must be &lt; \" ","answers":[" Your message didn't come though quite right, but I'm guessing you thought it should be &lt;= rather than &lt;. The buffer is 100 bytes long which allows for at most 99 visible chars, plus the '\\0' to terminate the strings. ",[" oh oz no I meant scroll.s has 'mush' instead of 'must' ",[" It's too late to fix it in assign1.zip. Everyone will have already downloaded it (won't they?) with the incorrect message. Maybe some people will decide to fix it ... so we'll have to allow either spelling in the test cases. "]]," oh yeah i noticed that too "]},null,null,null,null,null]}